Okay, it's done.
Uhhuh.
Okay.
[Music]
I'm ready.
Hello. I think we are on already. Um I
am we have started and I have to
apologize for being late and I'll tell
you why I'm I was late. I just walked in
the house. I was at camp meeting and um
and I left and there was so much traffic
on the way here instead of half an hour.
The drive was 1 hour. I was at camp
meeting at SoCal. I am in central
California
and my presentation is right before
Pastor Ivor's presentation.
Uh so yesterday and today um we're doing
presentations all week actually and
yesterday I got to see Pastor Ivor and
Atante and today I got to see Pastor
Ivor not for very long though barely
just to say hi and I have to say it's
been such a blessing. It's been such a
blessing. So, we're doing presentations
all week long, Monday through Fridays.
And I even told Pastor Ivory yesterday
because I think it's so providential
that my presentation is at 2 p.m. His
presentation is at 400 p.m. So, it's
backto back same exact room uh almost
exact same people. Of course, his
presentation has a lot more people. My
presentation is at the same time as many
others, but his presentation is like by
himself. Nobody else is doing
presentations at that time. So it's
really wonderful. Uh but his my
yesterday especially I got to talk about
Daniel one and just this providential he
came in and talked about Daniel 2 and
then 7 8 9 10 or 11 and 12.
I mean this was all just very very
providential. It was such a huge
blessing. This has been so wonderful at
camp meeting. So, I'm just very very
blessed. I'm very blessed with be with
you today. As I promised, uh, the last
two times we've been talking about
diabetes. This is a four-part series.
And today we're doing part three all
about exercise. What is the best
exercise for not only people with
diabetes and pre-diabetes but everyone
who wants to prevent those conditions
and all the other metabolic diseases
that are associated
with diabetes, pre-diabetes and
everything that is associated. Okay, but
before we get started as always we need
to pray. Let's not forget about that
very important part. So let's have a
word of prayer. Dear heavenly father,
thank you so much for all the blessings
you give us that we just do not deserve.
Thank you for your love. Thank you for
your word and especially thank you
today. We want to thank you for the
health message you have given us. That
is such a blessing for us, for our
health, for our bodies. And we ask you
to be with us today that the technology
works and that uh everyone who is
connected today and that who will be
connected and that who will see this
program uh later maybe uh that will be
blessed by it and that everyone
um who is blessed by it will also share
it so that other people may learn not
only how to take care of their bodies
but also about you who is our maker, our
healer. our God. Thank you so much for
everything and everything we pray and
ask in your name. Amen.
Okay friends, so we are talking again
about reversing and preventing
diabetes, pre-diabetes and all the
conditions that are related to it. And
as we have said in the last two
presentations,
the conditions that are uh related to it
have to do with the root cause. I hope
everyone remembers what the root cause
is. Uh and it has to do with I hope you
remember the root cause is
insulin
resistance.
If you don't remember or if you don't
know because it's the first time you
connect, you can go back to part one and
part two of this series
and also to the first two true health
Tuesday that I did and it was called 10
days to better health and that's where I
go really deep into this topic of
insulin resistance. Now I want to as
always say that this presentation is not
meant to be medical advice. It's meant
to be educational. Okay? So this is for
your knowledge, for your education.
And also as always, my spiritual
disclaimer is that everything that I
teach, everything that I present will
always be or I try at least to be in
harmony with the Bible and the spirit of
prophecy. I try. If not, let me know.
But I try to always present everything
in accordance and in harmony with the
Bible and the spirit of prophecy. And
that is in Isaiah 8:20. It says to the
law and the testimony. If they do not
speak according to this word is because
there's no life, no light in them. And I
always repeat this because there might
be people today who have not seen my
past presentations.
And the other thing is that I always try
to present things that have a solid
scientific evidence because the spirit
of prophecy has taught us the importance
of science. The knowledge of science, a
knowledge of science of all kinds is
power and advanced science shall be
taught in our schools as preparation for
the work that is to precede the closing
scenes of Earth's history. I think we
are witnessing right now. the closing
scenes of earth history. I don't know if
you believe that but I do. A practical
knowledge of the science of human life
is necessary in order to glorify God in
our bodies.
Ah yeah. What is the best diet? Thank
you Wendy for your question. What is the
diet best diet for neuropathy? That's an
excellent question.
If neuropathy is caused by diabetes, it
would be the diet for diabetes for
reversing uh diabetes. And that is the
diet that we talked about two weeks ago,
presentation number two in this
four-part series. Um, and that is the
whole food plant-based diet. But to be
quite honest with you, the presentation
that I did at 2 p.m. at camp meeting, I
said the exact same thing that I'm going
to tell you right now. The best diet for
every single human being is the whole
food plant-based diet. And I'll tell you
why. Is the diet that is found in
Genesis 1:29.
And that is the diet designed by God
for us. God is the maker of our bodies.
This is my belief. I hope that is also
your belief. And just like when you buy
a new truck, let's say you go to the
dealer, buy a truck, and let's say you
forgot whether you're supposed to put
gas or diesel. Let's you you're probably
not going to ever forget because you buy
and you know what you're getting, right?
But let's say you forgot. So you get
home. Oh, oops. What am I supposed to
put? Okay. Well, you get the manual out
of the glove compartment, most likely.
Open up the manual. Maybe page 129. It
says right there. I'm just making it up,
right? But you look up where what kind
of uh what kind of fuel am I supposed to
put in this truck? Oh, okay. This is a
diesel truck. I'm going to go to the gas
station and look up where the diesel is.
Okay, here's the diesel. I'm going to
put diesel in my truck because what
happens if I put gas in a diesel truck?
It's going to break down. It's not going
to work. Now the thing about it is God
made our bodies so resilient,
so wonderfully made that we can put the
wrong fuel for a while and it'll
continue to work for a while but not
forever. It will start to break down
sooner or later. The correct fuel is
told to us in page one,
page one of the manual. You know which
manual I'm talking about, right? The
Bible. Unless it's large print, it might
be page two. But most likely will be
page one because it's chapter one, book
one, Genesis 129 says right there
which diet God gave us. And it is a
plantbased
diet. God made our bodies to be plants.
We're not carnivores. I was telling the
group at 2 o'clock at camp meeting that
keto is not even the thing anymore.
Now it's carnivores.
Carnivore diet. It used to be five even
five years ago is fringy. Fringy. You
guys, have you heard of the carnivore
diet? By the way, how many of you have
heard of carnivore diet? My goodness,
there's so many people pushing it. The
the group I was talking to, there's
probably like 50 at least 50 people,
maybe more.
So many of them had heard of the
carnivore diet. It's becoming
mainstream.
Even within the church, there's people
doing it.
Carnivore. We're talking people who are
eating nothing but meat.
We are not carnivores.
Our bodies are not meant to eat meat.
We're not even omnivores.
I'm serious about this.
I You know how I know this?
When I had a a golden retriever, now I
don't. She passed away. She was 12. No,
she was almost 15 when she passed away.
You know what? My golden retriever, you
know who gave it to me? Pastor Ivor, I'm
not kidding. Okay. She lived to be
almost 15. I I got the I got her from
them. Anyway,
when I had her,
we would I would take her out for walks
and sometime we lived in, you know, kind
of ruralish area. Sometimes there'd be
dead deer on the road. Roadkill.
You know what she would like to do when
there was dead deer on the road? You
know what she wanted to do? She wanted
to go sniff the dead road the roadkill
the dead deer.
How many of you
if you see dead deer or dead anything
want to go sniff it?
Put a one in the chat. If you like to go
sniff roadkill.
There's going to be zero ones in the
chat. No once. I know. Our
instincts are completely against seeing
dead bodies, dead animals.
We are grossed out by that
because we are not carnivores. We're not
even omnivores. Dogs are omnivores. So
are bears. They eat berries and they eat
fish. Oh, there's a Valerie. You like
roadkill, Valerie?
Maybe you misunderstood me. That's okay.
What I want to say is that humans are
not
okay. Got you. You know what I mean?
You're getting my point. I think I hope
you are. Humans are not even omnivores.
We are
cultural omnivores. What do I mean by
that? We have taught ourselves to eat
meat.
But what how do we eat it? We have to
cook it.
How many animals in nature cook their
meat?
How many animals in nature put barbecue
sauce in their meat?
How many animals in nature put it
between buns,
cut it up in steaks, put it on a
barbecue or whatever, grill it? None.
How do they eat it in nature? with the
fur, with the nerves, with feathers,
with whatever blood. That's how animals,
even omnivores, eat it. Both carnivores
and omnivores have the same teeth.
They're canines. See, people who say
they they think they eat meat naturally
or whatever. Oh, look at my canines. Oh,
okay. Look at your canines and then look
at your cat
and compare your canines with your cat.
They're not even close. Okay, that was a
really big digress. Sorry about that.
But that was a good question.
A good question. Thank you, Wendy. All
right, I'm going to skip this. God wants
us to have common sense. See, I just
used common sense, you guys, to answer
Wendy's question.
All right,
today's topic is
diabetes
again and pre-diabetes which are
completely reversible uh or pre-diabetes
is completely reversible and so is
insulin resistance. What we have found
in uh in the research basically is that
type two is to type two diabetes I mean
is reversible in probably above 80% of
the cases not 100% of the cases and the
reason why is because in some people
their pancreas will eventually stop
working properly after many many years
of overproducing insulin I don't know if
you remember this when we talked about
insulin resistance
And we said that people who have insulin
resistance sometimes start producing a
lot of insulin to compensate for the
fact that the insulin is not working
properly. Therefore, their glucose
levels start to go up and their pancreas
starts to respond to that by producing
too much insulin. And what happens is
after many many years of overworking the
pancreas, sometimes that pancreas
eventually stops working properly. And
so some for some people that's an
irreversible condition. The pancreas is
kind of um damaged.
So there might be some people who might
not be able to reverse it completely,
but they still could improve.
Therefore, we can always improve. So
lifestyle changes will always
always be worth doing. Now in order to
do that we need to then uh go to the
root cause. Now as I showed you before
some people will say and I know this
because some people have told me oh wait
a minute my doctor said type two
diabetes cannot be cured.
Doctors have told me that. Honestly I've
heard this from medical doctors. But
it's not their fault you guys. This is
what they were taught.
So, of course, they're going to say
that. That's what they were taught. And
it's because that's what the the
research told them, too. So, what I say
to people who say this is, well, the new
research shows that type two is actually
reversible. Because look, this paper
right here that I'm showing you is a
consensus statement from the American
Diabetes Association. I already showed
you this. This is all review. The
American Diabetes Association has this
consensus statement that says what? Are
you looking at the title?
How do we define?
I'm not saying the word. Good thing I
didn't say it. The ADA said it. Cure. I
didn't say the word cure. They said it.
They said it. So therefore, that means
they're saying they could be cured.
They're saying it. So you tell your
friends when they tell you, "Oh, well,
diabetes cannot be cured." Well, the ADA
said it can't. You show them this paper.
That way you say, "Hey, the ADA said
it." Okay.
Not in 100% of the cases, but some
cases. Thank you for from joining us
from Canada. Awesome. Thank you, Andrea.
Okay. So, what as I said, we need to go
to the root cause. The root cause is
insulin resistance. This is important to
mention because it's not only the root
cause of diabetes and pre-diabetes but
also all the complications.
Remember the complications
all the complications. See these these
are the complications.
There's cancer you guys. There's
Alzheimer's you guys. There's erectile
dysfunction.
PCOS.
You know what that is, right? Polycystic
ovarian syndrome. There's neuropathy.
Somebody asked about neuropathy. Who was
it? Wendy. There's neuropathy right
there too.
And there's all these other things. You
guys look at the the chart.
There's all these things.
Atherosclerosis obviously
uh hypertension.
These things can happen without the
diabetes. That's why I'm mentioning them
because you might not even have
diabetes. You might never have diabetes
and have these.
They have the same root cause.
You have to go to the root cause. That's
why the same diet works for everything.
And people ask me, what should I do if I
have hypertension? This
the same the same the same diet that
works for everything works because it's
the same thing. you address this.
What should I do for PCOS? The same
thing. What should I do for cancer? Same
thing.
What should I do for neuropathy? Same
thing. It's the same diet. It works for
everything because they're all
connected. Because God's diet works for
everything.
Okay.
So, the key number one for reversing
diabetes and pre-diabetes, we already
mentioned it. It was diet. We talked
about it two weeks ago, so go back and
watch it if you haven't. I'm not going
to repeat it because today we have to
talk about key number two. Key number
two is physical activity. And the reason
why I'm going to talk about it today is
because most people actually do not
understand this. If I go to a church or
an audience for any other audience for
that matter, actually I do this at my
work. Most people don't even are not
Adventists actually at my work and I ask
the same question. People answer the
same way. What's the best exercise for
diabetes?
What do you think people say when I say
what's the best exercise for diabetes or
for losing weight, for hypertension, for
heart disease, for this and that blah
blah blah. What do you think people say?
Because they say the same thing all the
time.
Well, similar actually. Some people
might say other similar things, but the
most common answer is
starts with a W.
Where do you think it is?
Walking.
And it's true. I'm not saying walking is
not good. Walking is the best as far as
cardiovascular disease. And I'll tell
you why. is this is the most accessible
uh kind of exercise for everyone. You do
not need a gym membership. You don't
need uh any special equipment.
And I mean you could technically walk
without shoes. Yes, Tara, you are
absolutely correct. Walking it's free.
It's accessible to everyone
unless you're in a wheelchair.
Okay, maybe not in that case, but for
most other people, it is accessible. You
might be able to walk without shoes. I
was going to say, but okay, if you have
shoes, it's better. So, most people can
do it,
but there's more to it. Okay, there
actually is more to it. So also I want
to mention oh uh producer can you move
my um picture up so I can actually read
it or else I can just open the actual uh
the actual thing. Let me just read it
from my Okay. It says according to
experts exercise provides benefit for
endothelial function. How many of you
know the word endothelial?
Endothelial tissue is the lining inside
of our arteries and our vessels. So
that's very important because that's
where the plaque starts to accumulate
inside the endothelial lining of the
arteries. And so they say should be the
first prescription.
What the first prescription? Well, along
with diet, I would say that's what I
would say. Along with diet, exercise
should be the first prescription when
treating
insulin resistance.
Huh? The first prescription. My oh my my
oh my. But I would say make sure you get
uh medical clearance. Number numero uno.
Get medical clearance. Okay. Especially
if you are you you are at the age above
40.
This is not normal. This is not normal.
Tokara says, "Walking is the most
easiest." Yes, it is the easiest. It's
also the most accessible exercise anyone
can do. I agree 100%.
This being sedentary is not normal. Is
not what our bodies are made for. It's
not what our ancestors did. Our bodies
are made to move. Okay? Move as much as
possible. Look at what an our ancestors
used to do for a living. If we think
about it, they didn't have to go to the
gym because they did this for a living.
Many hours a day. And think about the
movements, you guys. The movements
that were required for growing food
pretty much pretty much the same you
would do actually in a in a gym if you
think about it.
growing food, right? So, they didn't
have to go to the gym. They were doing
exercise out in the open. So, they were
getting the sunlight, the fresh air, and
the physical exercise, also the walking.
So, all of this they did not have to
pay. Think about cutting wood, the back
exercise, the shoulders, the arms.
All of this was also building muscle.
These ladies, what are they doing? What
are they doing? Do you see what they're
doing? They're washing their clothes.
They're washing the clothes in the
river. Think about the movement for
washing clothes. Think about that
movement. What parts of the body are
they moving? They're moving their arms.
They're moving their shoulders. Even the
back is getting some exercise. They're
not going to the gym,
yet they're getting muscular. Are they
not getting muscular exercise? And then
if they're at the river, think about
this. They have to go back home, don't
they? They have to carry the clothes
back home.
Do the clothes weigh more now that
they're going back home with their wet
clothes. So, think about the fact that
they're carrying weightbearing
exercise. You guys, no gym involved
here.
See,
so let's think about this. Our
ancestors, even people today, if you
think about this, in many regions of the
world, maybe these ladies are carrying
water, food, I don't know. There's
places where people are poor. They don't
have access have access to water, which
is very very unfortunate.
But
they're making they're doing more
exercise than many of us. Unfortunate.
Unfortunately, because some of us are
not taking advantage of the fact that we
have maybe more time. We have better,
you know, life and more opportunities
and yet we are not getting the exercise
we need to. They're getting some health
benefits. Our ancestors were getting the
benefits of physical activity without
needing to get the gym membership. Now
we need to get the gym membership
because we have uh we have engineered
our way out of these tasks
and some uh jobs today might require
some physical activity that's good
but I would say even physical activities
that have to do with uh jobs today
modern jobs like construction maybe even
field work might not include enough
cardiovascular activity like Takaro was
saying the walking. Okay. Well, a person
a person who walks in construction might
not get enough walking. They might be
doing exercise but they might need to
add the walking component here. Okay.
So, look at this job right here. Sitting
eight hours a day. You guys, you know
that they've said the experts are saying
that sitting is a risk factor almost as
bad at smoking. Have you heard that
before? will look it up because that's
what the science is showing. Sitting is
just as risky for your health as
smoking.
Sitting
and look at all, you know, there's so
many jobs that require sitting for hours
and hours and hours. So people, what the
experts are saying is every 50 minutes
or so, 45, 50 minutes, people need to
get up and at least walk five minutes,
walk around the office, go up a flight
of stairs, come back down, do something,
go outside, look at the flowers, the
trees, something because you need to
move those legs. Some people stand all
day like maybe teachers. Okay, that's
better than sitting, but you still need
to walk. you still need to do some
cardiovascular and
also some resistance exercise which I
will talk about. Okay. So, Takara has
heard about what I just said that
sitting is bad. Now, we were talking
with regards to diet. Oo, some Takara
said sitting a lot. See, there's a lot
of people who sit too much. I would say
even I sometimes sit too much. So, what
I have done, I'll tell you what I have
done. Uh, I bought a $300
little walking pad. I guess you would
call it a treadmill. Also, $300. It
wasn't very much money. And I put it
under a desk. I already own the desk.
It's a tall desk and I already had it,
so I didn't have to buy it. But you can
also buy a tall table or desk and put a
walking pad if you can afford it. I It
only cost me $300.
uh bought it online and I use it as a
walking desk and uh if you can afford
it. Now some people you know don't work
at home so might not be able to do it
but some people do bring it to work. So
I know some people have these kinds of
arrangements at work. Other people don't
have a walking thing at home but don't
but at least stand at work. They're able
to have a standing desk at work. So,
Takara says she goes to work on lunch
break. That's an excellent idea. Oh,
there's a lake. That's even better. My
goodness. What? That's That's very nice
to have a lake nearby. Oh, how pretty.
That's wonderful. Okay, so now we're
looking at here at the picture that I
showed you before. This is a picture
that I showed you representing insulin
resistance. And what we see here is the
fat inside the cells. Remember this the
fat also called the technical name for
this is intrammyiocellular
lipids. Remember that intramyiocellular
you can look it up you guys. This is the
scientific name for it. Fat inside cells
intramiocellular lipids which are
blocking. So the little stickman that I
you know drew there I guess drew as in
uh digitally drew I guess. Uh the stigma
represents the insulin. The insulin is
in charge of putting the glucose inside
the cells if you will, but it's blocked
by the fat. Okay? So, this is called
insulin resistance.
So, the uh what I want to say, look at
this. Look at this. You guys look at the
screen. If you're not looking at the
screen now, it's a good time to look at
it because this study that I'm showing
you literally says literally says that
exercise
works like insulin.
Literally
exercise works as insulin. Literally
does the same thing. Puts the glucose
inside the cells. Wow. So what I
recommend you guys, I always tell this
to diabetics. What's So okay, I'm going
to ask a question. What is the best time
to walk?
Trick question. What's the best time to
walk? Because people give me all kinds
of different answers when I say, "What
is the best time of the day to walk?"
And I will say there's two different
answers for that question.
Powerful. Yes. Takara, isn't that
powerful? Okay, what's the best time to
walk? You guys put in the chat
because there's two different answers to
that question. I'll tell you what. It
depends on whether you have diabetes or
not.
So,
it depends. Okay, Melissa, interesting
statement. Yes. Gotcha. Now, what's the
best time to walk? It depends on whether
you have diabetes. In the morning and in
the evening, says Takara. Oh, you're in
the right track right there. I'll tell
you what. Anytime, says Hatti. I don't
know how you pronounce your name. Hatti.
Hottie. Hottie. Hatti or hottie. Okay,
never mind. Um, hati. I hope you I'm
saying it right. And please forgive me
if I'm not.
I'll tell you what. If you have if Okay,
no. Let's start with don't. If you don't
have diabetes,
exercise at whatever time you will
exercise because it's better to exercise
at any time than not exercise at all.
So, Haddie is correct with that. She
says anytime or he. I could be it could
be a hect. I don't know. I'm sorry. Um,
anytime is better than no time at all.
So, is absolutely correct. Anytime.
But here's a big butt.
If you have diabetes,
Tara is in the right track.
Exercise
after. Listen to me. Listen. This is a
good time to really pay attention. Open
your ears as open as you can.
If you have diabetes,
exercise after meals.
Did you hear that? Exercise when?
after
meals. Why? The reason is the the reason
is the study that you're looking at
right now. Hope you're looking at the
screen. Because exercise works like
insulin.
So what am I talking about? When you eat
after dinner, says to car. Yes, that's
the best time. Actually, one of the best
times because that's when your
metabolism is very, very low. it's
lowest, right? Your metabolism is
actually higher in the morning
and it starts to slow down in the
evening. So when you eat, if you're
diabetic and you eat a meal, your blood
sugar starts to go up immediately.
It reaches a peak at around 45 minutes
after the meal. And if you're diabetic,
that peak will probably be higher than
normal. But if you finish the meal, put
down the fork, and instead of sitting in
a couch, now if you work, this will
might not be possible. But let's say you
don't work or you have the ability, you
have some flexibility in your uh
schedule. If you have the ability to
after eating, even if it's 10 minutes,
listen to me, even if it's a 10-minute
walk, if it's brisk especially, but even
if you can't do a brisk walk, even if
it's five minute, whatever walk you can
do, okay? If you go for a five minute
walk, 10 minutes better, 15 minutes is
best, of course. If you go for a walk
immediately after finishing that meal,
breakfast, lunch, and dinner, and if you
can only do one, dinner would be best.
Like Takara says,
if you go for that walk, that peak will
never be as high
because you just went for that walk and
that exercise walk worked just like
insulin. You see what I'm saying? So,
some of that glucose, you see what it
says right there? glucose uptake,
meaning the exercise opened up those
channels to put that glucose inside the
cell
just like insulin.
What a wonderful thing this is. God is
so wonderful. God has given us true
remedies. That statement in ministry of
healing when it lists all eight
principles of health after listing all
eight of them it says these are the true
t r u e true remedies exercise is one of
them it works just like insulin you guys
it puts the glucose right into your
cells
isn't that wonderful I don't know how
many if you want to say amen feel free
put it in the chat big amen all capital
letters
Because this is amazing. Tell all your
friends about this. Insulin spikes
quickly at to its peak after a big meal
especially. Absolutely. So
go for that walk. So if you have the
time to do 20 minutes, all the better.
If you have do if you can do 30 minutes,
all the better. But okay, if you're a
diabetic, what's better to walk? to walk
one hour or
three times 15 minutes each after a
meal. I would pick 15 minutes each after
a meal. Amen. Amen. Amen. I'm getting
all the amens. Thank you you guys. Thank
you you guys. Exercise is a free natural
medicine. Yes, absolutely. All eight of
them. And exercise is a big one. So this
is what I want to uh emphasize today.
How exercise is medicine. Food is
medicine. Exercise is medicine too. You
guys, all eight of them are. But I don't
think people realize how wonderful these
things is. So I I'm showing you the
inside of a cell. You see the inside of
this cell?
The little thing right here down at the
bottom with a it looks like a bean with
a wiggly thing inside. Looks like a
bean. Look at it. Right at the bottom at
the edge. It's like like a little bean
with something inside. It's that's
called the mitochondria. Okay. Yes.
three 15 minute uh walks are better.
Yes, absolutely. But what I want to show
you right here, the cell, the inside
thing inside the cell is called a
mitochondria. Mitochondria. Just
remember that because
um the mitochondria are what produce the
energy for the muscles to work. So what
I'm showing you here are muscle cells.
And it also shows the mitochondria right
here on the left. These mitochondria
are energy production
uh furnaces if you will. These are the
little organels inside the cells that
produce the energy in muscle cells and
all cells really. But what I'm showing
you here are muscle cells. And
I the reason why I'm showing you all of
this is because look at this study.
Look at this study. Well, you can see in
the title, restoration.
See, restoration. Oh, you know what? I
told you I was at camp meeting today.
And the theme. Wow. This is just
providential. The theme of camp meeting
this year, restore. The word, just the
word restore. They're talking about
spiritually, right? Restor restoration
spiritually. how God can restore us in
so many ways. And here it says
restoration also. I'm just making the
connection here because the the true
remedies God has given us restore us
physically.
God wants to restore us in all ways.
Physically, spiritually, mentally,
emotionally, in every single way, God
cares for us because we are whole
beings. He cares for us in every single
way.
Anyway, digress. I digress. Okay.
Restoration of muscle mitochondrial
function. Mitochondrial function and
metabolic flexibility in type 2 diabetes
by what?
By what?
Exercise
training.
Exercise training is paralleled by
increased myiocellular fat storage and
improved
insulin sensitivity. Do you see this?
What's going on here? Exercise is
improving your insulin
sensitivity. That's what I want to
that's the main point right here. How
exercise works to improve insulin
sensitivity by improving
restoring
mitochondrial function. In other words,
those little furnaces inside the cell
are starting to work properly,
improving, burning the energy more uh
properly, more efficiently, and just
more working properly. That's the name
of your ministry, Takara. Is it for
Zion? VI or for Zion? Restored Ministry.
I love it. Love it. Love it. I'm just
making so many connections today. So
wonderful. This is awesome. Okay, so I
showed you this before. all the fat. You
see the top uh picture that's normal,
but the bottom you the bottom picture
what we're seeing here is all the fat.
The atapose tissue is like kind of more
like the visible fat, right? So adapose
tissue, the love handles if you will,
that's visible fat, especially the the
subcutaneous fat because you see it if
you look at yourself in the mirror is
right there. But the intrammyiocellular
lipid, the ones on the right, right? So
that we're zooming in, if you will, into
the muscle cells. That's the kind of fat
that produces the insulin resistance.
They want the fat inside the cell, the
droplets inside the cell. That's what's
producing the insulin resistance. I
think I showed you this before, so I'm
just reviewing here.
Uh, when are you Okay, so I'm I'm being
asked the question. When are you
starting a plant-based eating plan
group? Well, at work, we just started
Sunday. It's a Spanish group, though.
I'm going to start a group uh in English
in Santa Cruz in August 17th. This is
all uh in Santa Cruz County though. But
you know what? I'm throwing you guys a a
challenge out there because guess what?
This could be health ministry, you guys.
And I know you're starting a uh
evangelism school. And health is
evangelism.
I can show you because I've done this
many many times. There's presentations
that I've done on health evangelism. And
Ellen and Ellen White, Sister White says
that health is evangelism. In fact, she
calls it health evangelism. She uses
that term you guys health evangelism
because she says that there will come a
time when this is the kind of evangelism
we'll be we'll be using.
Jesus healed more than he preached. And
he sent his disciples.
He said, "Heal the sick first and then
tell them the kingdom of God is has
come." So heal the sick and then preach
the gospel. This is evangelism. So I
throw the challenge at you guys to do
health evangelism where you are. You can
partner with the local church. That's
what we have done here. We have
partnered with the local SDA church. We
bring in people that are non-Athenist to
do our 10day program.
And you can use I give you full
permission to use the PDF in my website.
Some of you probably have already
downloaded it. It's the Daniel challenge
10day program. You can use it, use it
freely or make your own if you want.
Use a whole food plant-based diet. You
can even get the devices to do biometric
testing if you want. How I learned about
these biometric testing devices. When we
used to do health clinics at our church
before COVID, we used to do dental
clinics and we used to do vision
clinics. This is all health evangelism.
Also, we used to do these clinics at our
churches and we used to do health
screening along with the dental and
vision services. That's how I learned
about these little devices. Now, they're
a little bit expensive, but there's
cheaper ones, too. So, you can if you
want. Now, I would uh recommend that you
have nurses or MAS, medical assistants,
somebody who has some kind of license to
do the poking of blood because this
require you know a little bit of of a
blood sample.
and do biometrics or just take their
blood pressure, their weight, whatever.
Or you don't have to do anything. Just
do the 10-day program at you can partner
with a church or you can, you know, rent
a hall or you can ask a nonprofit. You
can do it at the library. You can do so
many things. You can do it at home, at
your house. There's so many ways to do
it. You can do it online. You can do a
Facebook group, a WhatsApp group.
There's so many ways to do it. Invite
your friends, co-workers,
uh friends from school, neighbors,
family members. Do it. This is This is
evangelism.
I even made a calendar for churches. you
I can send it to you if you want but
basically a 12 month calendar for
churches to do one month because I heard
this from Fred uh Hardinch who used to
work at uh the um general conference
he's retired now but he basically used
to say go to churches and say even if
you do a once a month program at your
church even if it's just a cooking class
at your church but do it every month
because the consistency is the key
that's health evangelism invite your
neighbors to your cooking class at the
at your church. Just do a cooking class.
That's it. But have your little, you
know, I don't know, steps to Christ.
Have some little magazines. Have
something there. Have something that
introduces people to Jesus. You don't
have to push it. Just do a cooking
class. Have a prayer. Tell them that why
you do this. Tell them why you do this.
Because our body is a temple. That's it.
That's all you have to say. Our body is
a temple of the Holy Spirit. We believe
in this. We believe that God gave us
this diet because we believe in God.
Boom. That's it. That this is how why
did Jesus heal?
Because this is what opens people's
minds
to the gospel. Once you heal them,
they're open. That's what Jesus did,
right? Once he healed them, he opened
their minds to accept the gospel. That's
what that's why the health message is
also for not just for us but to share.
Anyway, I digress. See how much I
digress. Sorry about this, but I think
this is important. I really really do.
All right. So, I have been accepted.
Awesome. Takara, wonderful. Health
evangelism is the right arm.
Thank you for for reminding us of that.
Yes, it is the right arm. It needs to be
restored just like that. uh story in the
Bible of the of the man with the the
right the arm that was uh that was not
well and Jesus said extend the hand the
right and it was restored the right arm
of the third a or the the three angels
messages the first angel's message has
the health message in it glorify God how
do we glorify God how how do we glorify
God by keeping our bodies healthy.
Anyway, digress. Okay, I'm just going to
skip some of these things very quickly
because this one just basically says the
same thing what we said before. I'm
going to skip this, you guys. Uh because
you can look up this, take a P, just
look it up later. Look up the uh
references and you see what it's saying.
Okay, it's basically saying that people
who are sedentary have a lot more
intramiocellular fat in their cells.
That's basically what it's saying. But
when you are more active, you don't.
What kind of exercise is best for
diabetics? We already said walking,
cardiovascular activity.
Christ healed them and then he beckoned
them to come and follow me. She got it
basically. That's it. That's the best
way best way to summarize it. Thank you,
Takara.
What kinds of exercise are best for
diabetics?
Okay. So, we're going to talk about what
the recommendations are for diabetics.
And rem remember guys, when we say
diabetics, we really mean anybody who
has any metabolic diseases, okay?
Because they're all connected. So, when
we say diabetics, fatty liver,
hypertension, cardiovascular disease,
and just about every other thing because
they're all connected. So, diabetic is
just a word to include everybody else.
The recommendations are these are the
minimum.
These are just the minimum. Okay, look
at this.
150 minutes of cardiovascular activity.
How much is 150 minutes?
Two and a half hours. Not a day.
A week. Okay. A week. Plus, you see what
it says also?
Not just walking. Well, okay. Okay,
cardiovascular could be walking, but
also could be other things. It could be
riding a bike. It could be jogging, I
guess. It could be also do the
elliptical machine, maybe at the gym. It
could be swimming. That's other. So,
there's several kinds of cardiovascular
exercise. But as we said before, walking
is the easiest, cheapest, most
accessible. Okay? But look at this.
Okay? Not just walking. It says also
resistance training two or three times
per week. This is the recommendation.
I'll tell you why it's so important in a
minute, but this is the minimum.
Now, look at what they're saying here.
Watch.
It says that only 12%
of diabetics
follow their recommendation for
resistance exercise. Barely 12%.
And 41%
engage in any cardio.
Not even half. Not even half of the
people are doing cardio,
let alone resistance training. It
doesn't even reach 15%.
You guys, what's going on?
Why are people not getting better? Well,
because they're not doing what's the
minimum. the minimum
if they did just the cardio. Just the
cardio. If they did it, look at what it
says right here. Following these
recommendations and just they're if you
really read them the the small print,
what they're saying is just the
recommendation for the cardio.
These recommendations result in a
reduction of what they're talking about
is hemoglobin A1C. That's your three
months average for glucose. It's not
the, you know, fasting glucose. It's
your three-month average.
Doing the 150 minutes a week results in
a reduction of hemoglobin A1C of 0.89%.
Now, you can say, well, that's nothing.
It's not even 1%. Well, it turns out
it's very similar to what is achieved
with diabetes medication. The diabetes
medication they're talking about is
metformin.
That is the most commonly
uh prescribed diabetes medication
which achieves 0.9%
reduction in A1C.
In other words,
walking
150 minutes a week, two and a half hours
a week does the exact same thing almost
as metformin.
You pick.
Metformin is not a bad medication in the
sense that it doesn't even have as many
side effects as others,
but exercise
has only good side effects.
If you think about it, exercise side
effects are always great.
They help with a bunch of other things.
There's no bad side effects. In other
words, unless you do it maybe in excess.
I mean, if you're running a marathon a
day, that might be a little bit too
much. Okay. Um,
and look,
so these are some of the benefits. Okay.
So if you're doing I would say okay the
amount depends on you because I can't
give you a umbrella recommendation for
everybody. It depends on your age and
depends of how your your health at the
moment. Uh if you're not doing
absolutely any exercise at all you might
want to talk to your doctor first. Uh
start small. Maybe if you if you can if
you have some limitations maybe start
with five minutes then increase to 10.
Uh so on and so forth. But here are the
benefits. Uh it uses energy. In other
words, it burns calories. It uh causes
small increases in metabolism. It
doesn't increase your metabolism a lot,
but it does increase your metabolism a
little bit. It improves muscle function.
It protects the heart. That's why it's
called cardio. The word cardio literally
means heart.
Uh Pastor Myers just started a
resistance training challenge last week.
I told you guys you guys need to you
guys need to join that. It's absolutely
wonderful. It's awesome. What he's doing
is wonderful. And I will tell you why I
think so highly of it in a minute. But I
want to tell you a quick story that I
heard from Dr. Hans Deal. The late Dr.
Hans Deal who I met in person is this
wonderful person. Five minutes. Oh no.
Okay. Better hurry up. Uh he told about
a person who went to Weimart, a patient
who they didn't even want to accept at
Weimart. Guys, he was so ill. He barely
could walk. He had a walker. He could
barely walk two or three steps. He ran
out of breath and he was so he had a
heart condition and the he he had been
told by the doctors basically go home
and die. They couldn't do much more for
him. Uh and the doctors of Weimar were
very worried that he might die at
Weimar. So they didn't want to accept
him. And so but they begged the family
was like, "Oh, please, please help him."
The doctor said he couldn't do anything,
whatever. So finally said, "Okay, fine."
They took him in. They were going to try
to do, you know, whatever they could.
And uh he was very, very sick. So sick
that he couldn't walk with the rest of
the patients. So at Weimar, Wemmer is
this place here in California where they
do this uh inatient uh kind of uh
treatment kind of thing where you can
stay and they do the new start program.
New start each letter starts for one of
the eight principles of health. Some of
you might be familiar with this what I'm
talking about, but it's a lifestyle
program and you stay I forget how many
days. I think it's like 12 days or
something like that. But you stay in
there, right? They feed you, they take
you for walks, they do consultations
with doctors, they do blood work. I
mean, they do everything and it's all
lifestyle anyway. So, they take you for
walks like a mile. You do trails. It's
up in the mountains. Beautiful.
And so, after each meal, I think you go
for walks. Anyway, this man was so ill
he couldn't walk. He he could hardly
walk a few steps. But right outside the
main door there's one of those flag
poles and it's like in a base like a
round thing and the the cars can go
around it, right? One of those things
like a round thing. I I don't know the
name of it. But he thought, "Okay, I
can't walk a mile." So they went for one
mile walks, I think. And he thought,
"Okay, well I can't walk with him for
one mile. Maybe I can go around this
flag pole.
He couldn't go the whole way around the
flag pole. He did like a quarter and he
had to come back to his room.
He couldn't do the whole thing. That's
how bad he was. He's how sick he was.
The second day he did like half, you
know. The third day he a little bit
more. Eventually he did the whole flag
pole. You know, by the end of the
program, I forget how many days. I'm
sorry. I think it's like two weeks.
By the end of the program,
he did a mile.
By the end of the program, this man was
like in his 60s. Okay.
He went home. Obviously, he changed his
diet, other things. He went home. Some
people they go home after the program
and they drop the changes like they stop
eating the food they don't follow up
right they don't follow but he did
Takara just mentioned all the eight
principles of hell the new start okay
there they are look at them anyway
this man did he followed through with
all eight of them he continued eating a
plant-based diet God's diet Genesis 129
diet he continued doing the exercise. He
started do going around the block. He
eventually did several blocks. Then he
started hiking. He started hiking you
guys up, you know, nearby areas, started
nature walks and stuff like that. And he
did everything, the water, sunlight,
temperance, all of the rest, trusting
God.
So he would, you know, keep up with new
uh with uh with Weimar. He would, you
know, tell them how he was doing. He was
going out for hikes. So a couple times a
year I think he would send them updates
of how he was doing. So oh you are going
to for he hikes like two miles high,
three mile highs. But after a couple of
years, three or four years the
communication stopped. They lost track
of him. They lost track of him. And some
of them wonder what happened to this
man. You know I wonder it's been a few
years, six, seven years they hadn't
heard from him.
But after 10 years,
they got a postcard. This was years ago.
Okay, so postcard, who uses postcards
anymore? I don't know. But this was back
in the 90s, I think, or whatever. Do you
guys remember postcards?
You know what I'm talking about, right?
Postcards. I don't know. Many of you
young people might not know. Postcards.
You know where from? It was from the
Himalayas.
A postcard from the Himalayas.
Kiss from who?
The this man.
What was he doing up in the Himalayas?
He was going up the Himalayas, you guys.
Not only did he not die
that time he went to Weimar,
he eventually went around the flag pole.
He eventually walked a mile. He
eventually walked two miles, five miles.
Now he was walking up the Himalayas.
That's what somebody remembers postcards
to God.
That's what God's true remedies do.
That's what God can do. He can heal. He
can heal and he can save. He can heal
our bodies. He wants to give us life and
life abundant
and heal our minds, our hearts
and our lives, our lives.
Anyway, I digressed again. Okay, I want
to say again that after meals is best
times for diabetics
and here is the
research on that. Okay, I also want to
tell you that here's the they also tell
you here after meals, after dinner
especially, this is what it says. They
also say that high intensity interval
training is very very good for
diabetics, very good for diabetics. And
I'm not going to go too into in depth
into this because we're out of time, but
high intensity interval training is when
you walk slow and then fast and then
slow and then fast and you only have to
do it for 20 minutes. But what that does
is that it actually helps even more to
burn fat and to control glucose and to
improve mitochondrial. Remember the
mitochondria, those little furnaces,
mitochondrial capacity, meaning you're
burning energy more efficiently. That's
why you're improving your glucose
control. Here's the proof. I'm just
showing you the evidence. Okay? So,
that's in regards to HIT. In other
words, highintensity interval training.
You can look this up with more time on
your own. You can look up if you want.
That is if you want to see the evidence.
This is what it's talking about. Okay?
That's for diabetes, pre-diabetes, etc.
So, these are the recommendations with
regards to cardio.
Hopefully for diabetics 10 to 20 minute
minutes after each meal in total for the
day. If you can get to up to 45 minutes
that would be ideal. Hopefully every day
or at least five to six times a week.
And if you can do one hit um or
highintensity interval training,
maybe not every day, maybe a few times a
week, that would be super cool because
you would burn more fat and glucose
control. Okay, I want to tell you a
little bit about the strength training.
Why I think it's so important what
Pastor Ivor Meyers is doing. It's not
just for aesthetics, you guys. It's not
just to show your nice muscles and for
us ladies to look more toned.
It's not aesthetics.
Look at some of the benefits. Okay?
Improves metabolism
100% more than than walking. Walking
does hardly anything for your
metabolism. Why is this so important?
Because many people
have very broken metabolism, especially
if you have done dieting. If you have
tried losing weight time and time and
time again, and you have failed, your
metabolism is probably super low.
People, yesterday, someone approached me
at camp meeting. I was doing the health
presentation, and she said, "I eat very
little and I can't lose weight." Guess
why that happens? It's because your
metabolism is low. Do you guys remember
that show called the Best Loser? No.
What was it called? The uh what was it
called? Best Loser or something like
that. The I forget the name. That show
where people lost weight. Remember?
Uh forgot the name. Put it in the chat
if you remember. But it's a competition
where people lost a lot of weight and
they lost like 100 pounds or more and
they were in a ranch. Uh, put in the
chat if you remember the name of the
show, but they did a study with those
people that did the show many years
later.
They did a study and they found that
those people gained the weight back.
Number one, and they were using up 900
calories a day. The biggest loser. Thank
you. Thank you. The biggest loser. They
were burning 8 to 900 calories a day,
you guys. That's nothing.
800 900 calories a day. That's
starvation.
So they were barely eating anything a
day and gaining weight. Of course they
were gaining weight because they were
barely eating.
They were still hungry.
That's nothing. 800 calories a day. They
were probably of course they were eating
more than 900 calories a day because
their needs were 800 calories a day.
They were probably eating like 1,000
9,200 and they were gaining weight. your
metabolism is damaged by doing dieting.
And when I'm when I say dieting, I mean
like um small, you know, like low
calorie diet when you restrict your
eating to eat like c the cabbage diet.
Have you heard of that one? The cabbage
diet. You eat nothing but cabbage for
two weeks or whatever. Terrible stuff.
Okay. Doing these kinds of things. So,
like what I said in the beginning, our
ancestors did it naturally.
They were working the soil, cutting
wood, washing clothes, doing all this
stuff. They didn't have to go to the
gym. They didn't have to, you know, do
weights and stuff because they did it
every day just doing stuff. Now, we have
automatic washing machines. We, you
know, we don't cut wood to cook anything
because we have and it turns on by
itself, right? To cook. We're not to do
anything. Therefore, we lose muscle
mass. If you're anybody's here older
than 30, if you're older than 30, you
have been losing muscle 2 to 8% a
decade, every decade.
Because we're too sedentary compared to
our ancestors. our ancestors, they used
up their muscles. We don't
we don't because we are not working this
the soil. We're not growing our own
food. We're not cutting wood. We're not
doing any of that. Therefore, we're
losing muscle. The only way not to lose
muscle is either you go wash your
clothes in the river and start cutting
your own wood and do all of that or you
do strength training.
That's what can preserve your muscle.
And if you haven't been doing, you need
to change your body composition back to
what it should be. That's what makes
your muscle stronger. If you're older
than 60, you might say, "Oh, no. That's
just for young people. I'm too old." No,
you need to do it even more. Guess why?
Because if you're older than 60 or 65,
your highest risk is false. If you fall,
you might break a bone. The hip
is really bad. My grandma fell and broke
her hip. She never got up again.
Never.
You need to prevent that. You need to
make your bones stronger and your
muscles stronger. And for that, you need
strength training.
also prevents osteoporosis.
Facts. Thank you, Tara.
Facts.
It's just what it is. Okay. That's why
I'm so passionate about this. That's
why. So, now you know the why you need
to join Pastor Ivor. So, look at this
from diabetes care. This is for
diabetics, pre-diabetics, and anyone who
wants to avoid it. Twice a week
progressive resistance training
decreases abdominal fat
and improves what? Look at the title.
Are you looking at it? If you're not
looking at, look at look at it now.
Twice a week progressive resistance
training decreases abdominal fat. Some
of you don't like that abdominal fat and
improves
insulin resistance.
That's the root cause of all those
conditions we talked about. Remember
that big circle with all those
conditions? Well, here it is. Insulin
resistance.
And
this resistance training helps not just
the diet, not just the cardio, not just
the walking, also lifting weights. You
don't have to lift weights. Also, you
can use your own weight. You can do abs,
you can do push-ups, you can do all this
stuff. You don't have to buy weights.
There's other kinds of resistance
training that don't require weights as
you probably know. Okay, so here's more.
Uh there's how the uh this kind of
exercise actually helps your metabolic
rate. Very important because that means
you're actually burning more calories
even when you're sleeping.
Even when you're sleeping,
when your metabolism is broken, you're
not burning enough calories throughout
the day. But when your metabolism is
restored,
you're burning more calories, adequate
amount of calories throughout the day,
even at night.
Okay, so this is what basically that
that's what it's saying. This is the
conclusion. Basically, your metabolism
is improved on average by 5% if you're
doing this kind of exercise. At least
this study, that's what it found. And of
course, it helps with obesity and
metabolic syndrome. The metabolic
syndrome is when your lipids and your
blood pressure and your blood sugar is
all out of whack. And that's physical
activity is helping you. Look at this
lady. Look at this awesome lady. How do
you think she is?
You know what? This picture is from a
article that came out in the uh magazine
called
um
um National Geographic.
The year was 2005
and it was talking about something
called the blue zones.
It made the blue zones famous. National
Geographic 2005
20 years. I'm pretty sure it's 2005.
Made the blue zones famous. You guys,
there's one blue zone here in in the in
North America. Only one.
You know where, right?
Only one blue zone in North America. In
the state where I am, I just happen to
be in the same state as the blue zone in
North America. And that blue zone is
California.
Tokara thinks this lady is 85.
What about you guys? Anybody else? How
old is this lady? Because she is a
resident of Luminda. Whoa. She's passed
since because this was 20 years ago.
Okay. But in this picture, I'll tell
you,
she's 101.
101.
She's lifting weights.
She get up in the morning.
She do 20 minutes of bike and then she
lift weights and then she go she drive
her own car to go volunteer.
Very active lady. She passed away at 104
I think. No diseases,
no chronic conditions.
Isn't that wonderful? Isn't that
wonderful? That's how I like to go. Just
stay in my sleep peacefully. No
diseases.
Are you looking? Are you looking?
This is why I think strength training is
the true fountain of youth. Are you
looking?
Do you see the ages here?
My goodness.
Do you see what time they started
exercise? Are you looking? Do you see at
what ages they started? My oh my. It's
never too late. You guys look at Wendy
Ida. She's 61 in this picture.
What an example. She's my idol.
Ernestine
came on my aunt show. No way.
Oh. Well, now see this picture is old.
She's like 80 something now. You know
her?
Oh, you're so lucky. I think she's 80
something, right? I think she's 85 now.
I mean, she looks amazing. She looks
amazing. Do you see what age she
started? She started at 56. I'm not 56.
I'm not even 56 yet. I started at 39. I
struggled with weight my whole life.
I would walk, walk, walk, walk, gain
weight, lose weight, gain weight, lose
weight all the time until
I don't know if you guys remember years
ago, there was thing this thing called
P90X. I bought those videos.
I bought this v DVDs. P90X. It was all
strength training. I figured it out when
I when I saw this thing and I was like,
"Oh, this is it. I need to build
muscle."
I had been losing muscle by doing all
this, you know, dieting. You know what?
And you know, I don't I don't fault my
mom and my grandma, okay? This is all
cultural. The they grew up like this,
too. But my grandma and my mom were
always talking about weight.
The first time I remember thinking about
I need to lose weight when I was eight
years old,
literally.
because they were always talking about
weight,
but
they also always gave me desserts.
How can this be? They give you sweets
and then they tell you to lose weight.
How?
Chef Babette is also 74. I think I know
her. And look, she's my age. Well, how
old are you? You look great from the
little picture. I'm gonna have to look
her up. Okay, I'm going to look her up.
I think I'm I might have her on my
Instagram. She sounds familiar. I'm
going to have to I think I know who she
is. I'm almost sure I follow her on
Instagram.
Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. I'm going to look
her up. Anyway, you got Yeah, I know.
It's insane. Okay. So, anyway, so okay,
here's the proof, you guys. What I'm
trying to tell you is look this once for
a especially for females. No, for males,
for everybody, honestly. You're 43.
Well, you look amazing. You look you
look fantastic to car. I'm just gonna
say,
okay, some people have good skin.
Anyway, what I want to say is you guys
anyone the muscles
it's just it's just uh it just makes you
look younger. Okay. Um
look at this. But it's not about looks,
it's about health. Because look at this
picture. Okay. the body composition when
it's healthy and when it's not healthy.
Okay, the person in the middle has too
much weight. And so there's two ways to
become healthier. You're welcome,
Takara. There's two ways to become
healthier. You lose weight the healthy
way or the unhealthy way. If you lose
weight the healthy way doing uh weight
training, not just walking, not just
dieting, especially not just dieting,
you got to do it while doing strength
training or else you will lose muscle.
If you lose weight, listen, if you lose
weight and you're not doing strength
training, you will lose muscle just like
the Biggest Loser
people.
Okay? So, listen up. If you're trying to
lose weight and you don't do strength
training, you will be like the person in
the right. Do you see the difference in
the body composition? So this little
section over here at the bottom, the
person who's healthy all the way in the
left, all the way in the left we see
healthy
and the red is muscle, the yellow is
fat. That's the correct body
composition. When we say body
composition, that's what we mean. the
muscle and the fat. You want the right
proportions.
Now look at the right.
Do you see what's happening here? This
is the unhealthy. We see more yellow,
less red, more fat, less muscle. Why is
this unhealthy?
Not just because it doesn't look good,
you guys. It's because more fat gives
you insulin resistance. Therefore, you
have higher risk for cancer, for
diabetes, for atherosclerosis, for PCOS,
for n uh for neuropathy, for all the
things we mentioned you guys, for heart
attacks, for Alzheimer's disease,
for erectile dysfunction, for all the
things we mentioned. That fat is
inflammatory. Listen, that fat, that
yellow stuff you're looking at is
inflammatory.
It produces inflammatory cytoines.
Cytoines are these molecules that go
around your body producing inflammation.
You need some of it when you cut
yourself when you have some kind of
injury. You need inflammatory cytoines
just temporarily. You don't want them
chronically in your body. But the fat
produces inflammatory cytoines
chronically. You don't want that. Also
produces estrogen all the time. excess
estrogen for both males and females. So,
you have all these hormone imbalances,
both males, males and females. Okay? You
don't want that. Look at this person.
This is just illustrative because I want
you to look at the bottom. It says me at
130 lbs. And the right also says the
same thing. It says me at 130 lbs. But
wait a minute, this person looks
different. It's the same person, but it
looks different. The the two pictures
look different. It's the same person,
same weight. Why do the two pictures
look different? You tell me. Why does
this person look so different if she
weighs the same exact weight?
Why?
You tell me. Why does she look so
different in the two pictures? Why?
What's going on here? You tell me what's
happening here. Put in the chat if you
know what's going on.
Obviously, she's been doing something.
She's been working out. Probably
something's been going on, right? So,
she's probably been doing some strength
training.
So, why when people do strength
training, they build muscle. The muscle
mass is more dense, more condensed,
and that means is a little heavier per
volume.
She has more lean muscles in the pink
bra. Yes, that's correct. She has more
lean muscle. And the lean muscle, this
um the muscle mass is a little heavier,
if you will, per volume than fat. fat is
kind of more uh it has it's has more
volume per weight if you will. Let me
show you this what I want to say. You
see this
uh I think this is a little bit
exaggerated but it kind of uh explains
what I want to say. It illustrates the
point really well. Per weight muscle is
more condensed whereas uh the fat has
higher volume. Yes, muscle is heavier
than fat. That's exactly it Cheryl.
Thank you. That's exactly it. So, you
can weigh the same
and yet look different. What I also want
to say is there's another term for this.
You know what? There's another term. You
can h Did you know can can you put my
face back? Uh, producer
uh, Sister LJ, did you know?
You guys, did you know that you can have
normal BMI and be obese? Did you guys
know this? You can have Oh, what? What
did What? What? What? Let me repeat
that. You can have normal BMI and be
obese.
take it take a little bit of time to obs
to to process that in your mind.
You can be here's the other term I was
just going to say. You can be skinny fat
or fat skinny
but skinny fat sounds better. You can be
skinny fat. What does that mean by that?
You can have normal weight but inside
have the body composition
of an obese person
because you have the wrong body
composition. Excess fat and too little
muscle. And if you have normal BMI and
you have the wrong body composition,
even if you're normal weight, your BMI
is 24, your doctor said you you're good.
So, you don't even have to be overweight
or obese to have these
health problems.
As long as your body composition is not
right,
you can have these health problem. If
you have extra of the yellow stuff over
here, because this yellow stuff over
here, the atapose tissue is not just an
aesthetic issue. It's a health issue.
This tissue
produces inflammation, inflammatory
cytoines. That's why it's a health
issue. Okay? So, I'm not just telling
you this so you can look better in a
bikini. That's not it at all. It's about
health. Okay? So, strength training, we
can blow it up a little bit if you if if
we can. The strength training that we
recommend is at least two to three times
a week at the very least. You don't want
to do it every day. Why
you want to leave one day in between?
Because that day, so after you do some
strength training, let's say you lift
some weights or whatever you want you do
after, how do you feel? Do you feel a
little sore?
That's normal.
The soreness comes from those muscle
fibers breaking a little bit. And that's
not a bad thing because you put a little
bit of strain. you challenge your
muscles a little bit and that means that
they're going to rebuild a little
stronger because your muscles are smart
because God made them smart. So that
means that when they rebuild, they're
going to little they're going to say,
"Oh, I need to be ready next time this
person lifts that weight again." So I'm
going to make sure I'm ready next time
she lifts that 5 lb weight. So I'm going
to rebuild stronger. ready for the 5 lb
dumbbell. So next time it rebuilds it's
going to but that's going to happen the
next day especially during sleep. So you
need that sleep. Do not skip on the
sleep. Okay? So you need that break,
that rest time. Every time you do
strength training, make sure you have a
day after to rest.
I also put start slow. Ask your doctor,
especially if you're past the age of 40.
Don't start lifting 20 pound dumbbells
right away if you're a woman or 50 pound
dumbbells or whatever if you're a man.
Don't start, you know, doing super heavy
stuff. Ask your doctor. Okay. Start
slow. Okay. Got it. Okay. Other benefits
of strength training. We're going to
finish with this because I'm way past uh
but I just want you to know, okay, this
is not just uh for diabetes or
pre-diabetes. Look at what it says right
here. It improves bones. Well, I kind of
had mentioned this uh just in passing,
but I want to emphasize that what
strengthens muscle strengthens bones.
So, the best way to prevent
osteoporosis, guess what? Well, number
one, you need to avoid excess protein
because excess proteins produces acidity
in the body and guess how the body
neutralizes the acid.
I hope you know this, but the way the
body neutralizes the acid is by
releasing calcium from your bones.
And do you know where the calcium goes?
In the urine, out your body. You pee it
out. You flush it out of your body.
Literally.
Do you want that? I hope you don't. So,
that's how osteoporosis really happens.
It's not really lack of calcium because
there's populations in the world that
eat like 600 milligrams of calcium every
day and have zero osteoporosis and don't
drink milk. So, and the populations that
drink the most milk in the world are the
Nordic countries and also have the
highest rates of osteoporosis and
fractures. So, it's not lack of calcium
of lack of uh dairy at all. In fact,
what causes osteoporosis is too much
protein which leads to too much acidity
and losing calcium and number two not
doing enough of this because the
resistance exercise is what prevents the
loss of muscle which is what prevents
the loss of bone density.
Do you know? Okay. So, I hope you are
working on this. Especially if you're
young, you need to start young. You
don't wait until you're 65. But if you
are 65, you can still prevent further
loss of bone especi if even if you have
osteoporosis already. Okay. By work with
your doctor also
your uh blood pressure and prevent
strokes.
So there's all these additional uh
benefits also improve your lipids,
cholesterol, triglycerides even. There's
so many additional benefits. Now, I want
to tell you something. If you um well, I
mean, you can join Pastor Ivor, but if
you wanted something additional, maybe
for an older person, cuz this guide
right here, go to any uh search engine.
Doesn't even have to be Google. Any
search engine, but you can Google it.
Okay? Google the name of this guide.
Power up in 10. Just put the name in the
search engine. Power up in 10. Just like
that. And it will give you the results
should give you a PDF produced by the
state of California. It's just free. It
was produced by the health department of
the state of California for everybody.
Free. You click on it and it gives you a
PDF. It opens up. It's available in
Spanish as well in, you know, whatever
name in Spanish. I have it in I have it
in Spanish in my website. So, if you go
to my website in Spanish, you can
download from my website because there's
a link to it. But in English, it's
called power up in 10. You click on the
PDF, download it into your computer, and
it has 10 simple exercises that are
strength training that anyone can do at
any age at home. No weights needed. A ve
they're are very simple. You don't have
they're not advanced. In other words,
you can do without any uh equipment.
They're very for beginners. Okay?
They're for beginners. So, even people
who are 60 plus um people who haven't
done anything in their lives, okay? Very
simple stuff. You don't even need
special clothing. Nothing. This is
simple. Okay? 10. It's a whole body
thing. Okay. So, the 10 include the
whole body. Very very simple, very
non-threatening, non-intimidating. So,
this is another uh option for people who
are very very beginners. Okay, you can
do this. So, I just wanted to share that
with you. Simple and uh easy and free.
This man Linda
94.
My grandma died at 93. She had been in
bed three years.
This guy is 94. Look at how active, full
of life. That's what God wants for us.
Life and life abundant. That's what God
wants for us. And you know what? I
didn't put it in the presentation, but
there was an article in the LA Times
years ago when the blue zones became
really popular and it say Lomolinda
residents live more than anyone else in
California basically, but it didn't say
everyone. It it says why Luminda
residents live more than everybody else.
That's what the headline of this article
says, literally. Why Lumalinda residents
live more than anyone else? Because they
consider the body a temple.
What a what a witness to the b to the
world
these people these centinaries have
been.
And what I want to say is that when they
started following the eight principles
of health including the diet
in the 50s60s
there was no evidence scientific
evidence to back it up. Now we have all
the scientific evidence in the world.
They had nothing but faith, nothing but
the law and the testimony to back them
up.
Today we have all the the law, the
testimony, the Bible, all of that and
the scientific evidence and a small
percentage of us are doing it.
They are our example
I think
and so few of us are actually doing it.
So sad because Lomolinda has become only
more and more famous. People that are
non-ventist think we are all doing this.
Seriously, I speak to non-adventists all
the time and they talk about Lomalinda.
Oh yeah, Linda, Linda, Adventist study,
health study, blah blah blah blah blah
blah. And they talk to me like all
Adventists are doing this. They think
that
and we're not.
We're not.
It's kind of sad.
I think it's sad because God has given
this to us as a gift.
By the way, if you don't like weight
training, if you don't like going to the
gym, here's another alternative.
Free also, except for the seeds. You
might need to buy some seeds.
But it includes both cardio and strength
training, resistance training, but you
have to do more than just one little
tomato plant. Okay? You have to do more
than just that, but it actually includes
a lot of exercise. Okay? Let me read
some of this. Um, that's why I'm
restarting the uh restarting at the age
of 43. I'm getting back into training.
Yes, that's great. Uh, that I used to do
when I was in track and field. Awesome.
Time magazine, the blue zone of
Lomalinda. Yes. Yes. Uh, wonderful. Yes.
Yes. Thank you. Wonderful reminder. Yes,
Lever. Absolutely. Isn't it? These
people are giving us such good example.
We really need to give back to that. Oh
yeah, I wanted to show you this picture
of the the tools.
Gardening, it's like going to the gym.
Anyway, triceps, you can work triceps,
forearms, chest. Just like going to the
gym, you guys. Okay, I want to finish
with this uh with this uh verse because
one time, okay, I'm really passed my
time, but I'm sorry you guys. I just
want to share one little thing. I was at
a church one time and uh and so I was I
was had just finished my masters in
nutrition and so this person from church
came up and said, "Hey, I heard you're a
nutritionist." I said, "Yes, yes." "Oh,
so can you uh design a diet for me so
that I can lose some weight?" Because he
was a little bit round, right? Um so
yeah, he was kind of overweight. And so
he said, "Can you design us a a diet so
that I can lose some weight?" And I
said, "Sure. Uh, but can you make it so
that I don't have to exercise at all?"
And I said, 'Well, brother,
I don't think it works that way. And you
know what I said? I said, "Well, I don't
think it works that way because in the
Bible, God actually connected diet and
exercise from the very beginning."
And the reason why I think that is
because of this verse. He said, "Well,
in the sweat of thy brow, some of the
versions say with the sweat of thy
brow." This one says, "In the sweat of
your face, you shall eat bread." To me,
that's a connection between exercise,
physical activity, the sweat,
usually bread,
nutrition, diet, eating.
So when I was working as a nutritionist
at the clinic, I I used to work, you
know, nearby like 25 minutes away from
here at a clinic. I was a nut a clinical
nutritionist and I used to talk about
the diet and then exercise say, hey, you
need to, you know, like maybe walk a few
times a week and they go, well, how many
days a week do I need to walk?
And just joking. I would say, well, how
many days do you eat?
However many days you eat, walk. No, I'm
just kidding. That's just a joke. But
eat well. I mean, walk as many days as
you can because really
you're we're supposed to be moving our
bodies. The food is fuel for the
movement. So, you know, with the sweat
of thy brow, you shall eat bread.
I think God is making a connection here.
But that's just my personal
interpretation. Okay, that's just my
personal interpretation. Okay. To end, I
want to leave you my website again,
healthboard.net.
Just to remind you that number one,
there is a 10day plan there. Okay? You
are free to use it. Like I said, oops, I
don't have a picture of that. I thought
I had a picture of that. Um, but you
I've showed you before the picture of
the website and up in the top it says
10day challenge.
You go there. Just click on that and
then it opens up the page where you can
download the Daniel challenge. So
amazing. The Daniel challenge. I covered
Daniel chapter 1 at my presentation
yesterday. I think I mentioned this
already. I covered Daniel chapter one on
my presentation yesterday at the camp
meeting. And then came Pastor Ivor. This
is we didn't even talk about this. Okay.
Him and I. I talked chapter one. He
covered chapter 2. 7 8 9 11 and 12. He
covered the rest of Daniel. These things
are together.
God is so wonderful. Okay, now we're
done.
If you have any questions,
go to this website,
go to contact, contact me, contact us,
whatever it says. I forget. You can
write to me and I will try to answer
back in less than a week. I can't
promise any faster because this week I'm
doing presentations at camp meeting and
I'm also doing a 10-day program at work.
So, I'm super duper busy, but I will try
to answer as soon as I can. Okay,
two weeks. We'll see you again. I'm
doing part four of this fourpart uh
series. So, don't miss it. It will be
August
5. August 5. And I'm going to talk about
how to put it all together. It's really
hard sometimes to make behavior changes.
So, I'm going to talk talk about how to
change your habits. It's hard sometimes
to have um to have self-control.
I might even someday I'm going to do a
whole presentation of food addictions.
This is extremely important, but that's
a whole different uh topic. But next
week, we're gonna talk about how to Oh,
actually, we're also going to talk about
other things because I need to talk to
you about the benefits of fasting.
The benefits of other things for
diabetes and and uh and um and
pre-diabetes. I need to talk to you
about other things that are very very
important. Sleep and stress management
for diabetes and pre-diabetes and
insulin resistance. I need to cover
that. So, I'm also going to talk about
that actually. Okay, next presentation.
This is super duper important. Most
people don't even know about this. I'm
going to cover that also. Next
presentation. That's August 5th. Don't
miss it. Okay. If you have any
questions, let me know. So, thank you so
much. And you're welcome to Cara. Thank
you for being here, all of you guys. I
really appreciate you guys um for being
here with us live for connecting and uh
if any of you guys that connect later, I
also appreciate you watching as well,
please share, share and share and share.
Also like it because that means that
more people will engage with the video
if you like and share. Um, but remember
this is this is material that's meant to
be shared because that that way people
will know that this is uh biblical. This
is given to us by God. Okay, let's
finish with word of prayer.
Dear heavenly father, thank you so much
again for all the blessings you have
given us. We are not even worthy of the
blessings you give us every day. And we
ask you to forgive us if we have not
been worthy of your blessings. if we
haven't taken proper care of this body
temple. And we ask you to give us wisdom
and uh understanding so that we can
learn how to better care not only of our
bodies but also how to better be
representatives of of you and the and
the and be better ambassadors and to be
able to take this word to other people
who might be in need of healing from
you. Help us to take this word to those
who have these conditions and maybe are
desperate to know how to better take
care of themselves, how to improve their
health. And help us to t to take this
knowledge to them and also let them know
that you are a God who cares for their
health and their salvation, their their
uh eternal life. And thank you for being
always with us. Be with us the tonight,
the rest of this week. and um and bless
Pastor Ivor also who's presenting at
camp meeting and help us to be together
also on Sabbath. And we ask all of these
things in Jesus' name. Amen. Thank you
you guys. Good night to everyone. We'll
see you August 5th for True Health
Tuesday, but also all the programs for
Living Mana Online Church tomorrow and
Thursday, also Sabbath. Thank you very
much everyone. Good night. Good night.
C.